Guide to the Frank J. Donner Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Frank J. Donner papers
1897-1992
MS 1706
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
38.5
The papers consist of clippings, court documents, correspondence, publications, interview transcripts, writings, and other materials documenting the research, writing, and activism of Frank Donner. The collection includes a small amount of Donner's correspondence, multiple files documenting the activities of individuals who served as political informers, and subject files covering a range of political and social protest groups from the 1950s to the 1990s. The papers also hold a series of Donner's writings, including manuscripts from two unpublished books on the use of informers in the 1950s and of government malfeasance during the 1980s, as well as several unpublished articles.
Donner, Frank J.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Helen Donner, 1996 and 1998. Gift of A. B. Chitty, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audio tapes in Series III, boxes 42-46 may not be used.
Audiotapes and computer media in Accession 2003-M-016 are closed until processed.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and one addition: I. Correspondence and Personal Papers, 1953-1992. II. Informers and Surveillance Files, 1897-1983. III. Subject Files, 1941-1992. IV. Writings, 1950-1992.
Scope and Contents
The Frank Donner papers document the history and use of political surveillance in the United States, primarily from the late 1940s through the early 1990s. The collection also generally serves as a resource for researchers studying the history of the twentieth century American left, civil liberties struggles and the lawyers who fought them, and the American political intelligence establishment. The papers reflect Donner's political and intellectual work and interests in civil liberties, progressive political movements, and the government's use of surveillance and informers. The collection includes extensive documentation on every major political informer from the anti-Communist wave of the 1950s to the social protest movements of the 1960s and 1970s. The informer files include biographical information, court documents and testimonies, and interview transcripts with and about individual informers. The collection also holds files on a significant cross-section of the social and political protest groups of the 1960s through the 1980s. Finally, the collection includes manuscripts of Donner's writings, including many unpublished articles and two unpublished books. The papers hold relatively little biographical or personal information about Frank Donner.
Biographical / Historical
Frank J. Donner was a lawyer, journalist, historian and civil libertarian who remained active in the American left for the better part of five decades. From the first investigations of Communists by the House Committee on Un-American Activities to the Reagan-Bush years, Donner was a leading expert on the use of political surveillance in the United States. Donner's belief in the ideals of democracy and civil liberties led to a lifelong commitment to the social movements of the left. Over the years, Donner came to work with members of the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), numerous unions, the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), the Socialist Workers Party, Students for a Democratic Society, Weathermen Underground, Vietnam Veterans Against the War, the Black Panther Party, and the Nuclear Freeze and Sanctuary movements. During these many years of activism, Donner collected his own set of files to rival those of J. Edgar Hoover, documenting and cataloguing the abuses of American political power. "The files and each item in them," wrote Donner "became for me a form of remonstrance, a private protest against betrayal by the government of its democratic premises."
Donner's personal life history is difficult to trace. Born in 1911 in Brooklyn, New York, Donner was the child of poor, working-class parents. Donner received his college education at the University of Wisconsin, where he also received a master's degree in history in 1934. He graduated from Columbia Law School in 1937, and began working as a research fellow in legal history.
Donner began his legal career as a staff attorney with the National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) where he worked from 1940 to 1943. Upon leaving government service, Donner worked as an assistant general counsel, first for the Congress of Industrial Organizations, and later for the United Steelworkers of America. In 1947, Donner went into private practice, specializing in constitutional law, labor law, and civil liberties.
On several occasions Donner served as counsel for defendants brought before the House Committee on Un-American Activities, as well as various deportation and loyalty boards. So powerfully did Donner challenge these actions, that he was frequently named as a Communist by government informants and committee members. In 1956, Donner was himself forced to testify before HUAC about his activities while working for the NLRB. Throughout the questioning, Donner steadfastly refused to answer the question "Are you now or have you ever been a member of the Communist Party?" Instead, he challenged the committee's constitutional right to exist and the legal parameters of their questioning (a "typical Communist line" according to the Committee). Donner later dismissed the attacks as "a stupid smear."
The political practices of the McCarthy era compelled Donner to become an author. In 1954, he began a long and fruitful relationship with The Nation when he published a long article entitled "The Informer." This article marked the beginning of Donner's research into the careers of individual informants, especially the 1950s generation of former Communists turned celebrity informants and professional anti-Communists (particularly Louis Budenz, Paul Crouch, Manning Johnson, Harvey "False Witness" Matusow, Matthew "I Was A Communist for the FBI" Cvetic, Herbert "I Led Three Lives" Philbrick, Elizabeth "Anti-Communist Queen" Bentley and others). Donner began working on a book-length study of the informant system, but legal problems and various threats of prosecution for libel prevented the book from ever being published.
In 1961 Donner completed his first book, The Un-Americans, a study of the House Committee on Un-American Activities and the political resistance that the Committee provoked. By focusing upon the student opposition to HUAC, The Un-Americans marks a transition point in Donner's political evolution. With this book, Donner recognized the birth of a New Left that would be led by young people, students, minorities and women instead of traditional party structures such as the CPUSA. Donner enthusiastically dedicated himself to the New Left and reaffirmed his fierce opposition to the mechanisms of political surveillance and right-wing reaction that would soon be used to combat this youthful opposition.
Through the 1960s, Donner served as general counsel for the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE), while working privately as a civil liberties lawyer. During this time, Donner published a number of his most important articles and reviews for The Nation, Playboy, and Harper's, gradually turning his political attention away from HUAC and towards "Spies on Campus," to cite the title of his 1968 article for Playboy Magazine.
In 1971, Donner became the director of the American Civil Liberties Union Project on Political Surveillance, housed at the Yale Law School. There, Donner fully indulged his already well-established personal obsession with collecting information on "official attacks on non-conformity." He also began a program of interviewing political informants, especially the new generation of young infiltrators and provocateurs within the New Left. These investigations furthered Donner's desire to simultaneously catalogue the history of government abuses of civil liberties while placing such events within the broader context of American political theory and practice. The results proved to be very influential: in 1971 Donner published "Theory and Practice of American Political Intelligence" in the New York Review of Books, and by 1980 he completed his magnum opus, The Age of Surveillance: The Aims and Methods of America's Political Intelligence System.
The Age of Surveillance propelled Donner to the forefront of the national debate over congressional oversight for the FBI and, as Donner put it, "the use of intelligence as a mode of governance." Donner's attacks on the intelligence abuses of the past occurred just when he perceived a rebirth of government malfeasance under the Reagan administration. During the 1980s and early 1990s, having retired from legal practice, Donner was principally involved in two major writing projects: a companion book to Age of Surveillance on the history of police repression (published in 1990 as Protectors of Privilege: Red Squads and Police Repression in Urban America ), and a book on the Reagan administration, which was entitled "Exploring the Wreckage" but never published.
Until his death in 1993, Donner continued to publish articles in The Nation, while receiving numerous awards for his lifetime of service to the cause of civil liberties. Over four decades, Donner received the Tom Paine Award (1961), the Page One Award from the Newspaper Guild in 1972 for an article on Nixon's abuse of the grand jury system, the Sidney Hillman Award, a Lifetime Achievement Award from the Playboy Foundation for the First Amendment, and the highest honor bestowed by the American Civil Liberties Union in 1985.
Frank Donner died on June 10, 1993 at the age of 83. Donner was survived by his second wife Helen Brammal (his first wife Madeline died in 1985), his daughter Eleanor and son Peter, and five grandchildren.
Antinuclear movement; Communism -- United States; Harrisburg Seven Trial, Harrisburg, Pa., 1972; Informers; Police patrol -- Surveillance operations; Sanctuary movement; Bentley, Elizabeth; Budenz, Louis F. (Louis Francis), 1891-1972; Burton, Joseph A.; Crouch, Paul, 1903-1955; Cummings, William G.; Cvetic, Matthew, 1909-1962; Donner, Frank J.; Douglas, Boyd Frederick; Grathwohl, Larry; Honig, Nathaniel; Johnson, Manning, 1907-; Kornfeder, Joseph Zack; Lautner, John; Lemmer, William; Matusow, Harvey, 1926-; Mazzei, Joseph; Mosher, Thomas Edward, 1942-; Philbrick, Herbert A. (Herbert Arthur), 1915-1993; Scott, Cecil D.; Tongyai, Thomas; United States. Attorney General's Commission on Pornography; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation -- Corrupt practices; American Civil Liberties Union; American Civil Liberties Union. Project on Political Surveillance; American Indian Movement; Campaign for Political Rights (U.S.); Committee in Solidarity with the People of El Salvador (U.S.); Communist Party of the United States of America; Jewish Defense League; Legal Services Corporation; Movement Support Network (Center for Constitutional Rights); Seattle Liberation Front; Socialist Workers Party; Vietnam Veterans Against the War
- Correspondence and Personal Papers, 1953-1992; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically, the series includes biographical information, general correspondence, and memorabilia. Folders with letters between Donner and officers of various colleges and universities and members of the United States Senate and House of Representatives have been filed at the beginning of the alphabetically arranged correspondence. Correspondence of a topical nature can be found in each of the other three series.
  - Affidavits of Frank Donner [providing biographical information], 1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles and clippings about Donner, 1962-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
  - Correspondence
    - Colleges and universities, 1976-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - United States Congress, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - A-W (General), 1955-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6 - 8)
    - Aldrich, Nelson, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Berger, Sidney L., 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Caute, David, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Corsetti, George L., 1977-1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Gejdenson, Sam, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Gelbspan, Ross, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Golat, Solomon, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Gonzales, Henry B., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Jacobs, Jim, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Pauling, Linus, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Playboy Magazine, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Stanford, John W., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Weiss, Ben, 1973, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified, 1961-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Donner, Madeline [vital records of first wife], 1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - HUAC testimony [documents opposing Donner and accusing him of being a Communist], 1961, 1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hugh M. Hefner First Amendment Awards, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Resume, Circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Informers and Surveillance Files, 1897-1983; Series II
  The series mainly falls under two headings: Individuals and Localities. One folder of Bibliographies relating to informers is placed at the beginning of the series and three folders relating to "Non-political" informers (e.g. within organized crime syndicates) are found at the end.
  Arranged alphabetically, the Individuals section consists of interview transcripts, clippings, correspondence, writings, notes, government documents, court transcripts, and other materials relating to specific government and police informers. The files were compiled by Donner during the course of his research on government surveillance and the use of informers. The informers predominantly date from two distinct periods: the red scare era of the late 1940s and 1950s and the counter-cultural movements of the late 1960s and early 1970s. Substantial amounts of material relate to Elizabeth Bentley, Louis Budenz, Joseph Burton, Paul Crouch, William G. Cummings, Matthew Cvetic, George Demmerle, Boyd Douglas, Larry Grathwohl, Nathaniel Honig, Manning Johnson, Joseph Kornfeder, John Lautner, Harvey Matusow, Joseph Mazzei, Thomas Mosher, Herbert Philbrick, Cecil Scott, and Thomas Tongyai (a.k.a. "Tommy the Traveler"). The section also includes material on a few individuals who provided information about informers to Donner, but did not serve as informers themselves. Three boxes of note cards relating to specific informers are listed at the end of the section. Information on these cards directly overlaps with individuals documented in the main run of files. Researchers should consult Series IV for Donner's writings about individual informers.
  The Localities section documents surveillance activities in specific cities and universities. The files are not comprehensive and information relating to these and many other localities can be found throughout the Individuals section and Series III. Four folders of miscellaneous clippings, correspondence, and notes regarding surveillance on college and university campuses are included at the end of the section.
  - Bibliographies, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Individuals
    - "Stoolpigeon File", undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Ames, Margaret Louise, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Anderson, James, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - April, Fran, 1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Asche, Harold, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Baldwin, Bereniece, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Baxter, Charles, 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Becker, Carl
      General
      See: Series III. Subject Files, 1941-1992 Folder 467
    - Benner, Robert, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Bentley, Elizabeth
      - General, 1944, 1954-1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Articles [written by Bentley], 1951, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Biographical and testimony abstracts, 1948, 1951, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Clippings, 1937, 1948-1956 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1936, 1945, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 14)
        - Donner, Frank, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Golos, Jacob, 1940-1941, 1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Memoranda, 1949, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Notes and manuscripts, 1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - William W. Remington v. Elizabeth T. Bentley et al. [Bentley's testimony], 1949 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - William H. Taylor v. Washington Daily News
        - Deposition of Elizabeth Bentley, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 20)
        - Testimony of William H. Taylor, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 21 - 22)
      - Trial questions, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Berle, Adolf A., Jr., 1948 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Beynon, Mary Elizabeth, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Blanc, John Victor, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Blauvelt, Mildred, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Brown, David
      - Clippings, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - FBI reports, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Notes, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Statements and testimony, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Browning, Jeff
      - Correspondence with Donner, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Interview transcript, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Budenz, Louis
      - Anti-Budenz documents, 1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Articles re: Budenz [by Edwin Smith], undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Biographical materials, 1947-1952 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Clippings, 1930-1958 (Box 3, Folder 37 - 40)
      - Correspondence [includes personal correspondence of Budenz], 1930, 1951, 1955, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Divorce, 1936-1947 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Friends of Louis Budenz, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Index to writings and testimonies, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 45 - 48)
      - Statements about Budenz
        - Chavez, Dennis, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 49)
        - Lattimore, Owen, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - Testimonies of Budenz
        - Abstracts and summaries, 1946-1952, undated (Box 5, Folder 51 - 54)
        - Communism and Communist activities, 1949-1952, undated (Box 5, Folder 55 - 56)
        - Export policy and loyalty, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 57)
        - Immigration and Naturalization Service, undated (Box 5, Folder 58)
        - Tax exempt foundations, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 59)
        - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 60 - 62)
      - Writings
        - Anti-Communist writings, 1947-1957 (Box 6, Folder 63 - 69)
        - American Legion Magazine, 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 70)
        - American Mercury, 1950, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 71)
        - The Communist, 1933-1944 (Box 6, Folder 72 - 73)
        - Daily Worker, 1936-1951 (Box 6, Folder 74)
        - Labor Age, 1930-1932, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 75)
        - Pamphlets on Communism, 1936-1940 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Burton, Joseph A.
      - Clippings, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 77)
      - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 78)
      - Government documents, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 79)
      - Interviews [includes interview with Frank Donner and radio program audio cassette], 1975, undated (Box 7, Folder 80 - 82)
      - Legal documents, undated (Box 7, Folder 83)
      - Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 84)
      - Statements, 1973-1976, undated (Box 7, Folder 85 - 86)
    - Carey, James B., undated (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Chambers, Whittaker, 1949, 1964, undated (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - Churchill, Beatrice, undated (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Cook, Mary Jo
      - Biographical information, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 90)
      - Clippings, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Crouch, Paul
      - Biographical material, 1950, 1953, undated (Box 7, Folder 92 - 93)
      - Clippings, 1949-1950 (Box 7, Folder 94)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1945-1955, undated (Box 7, Folder 95)
        - Transport Workers Union of America, 1946-1947, undated (Box 7, Folder 96)
      - International Workers Order documents [includes photograph], 1932-1939 (Box 7, Folder 97)
      - Legal documents
        - Harry Bridges trial, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 98 - 99)
        - Armand E. Scala v. The Hearst Corporation, undated (Box 7, Folder 100)
        - United States v. Joseph Weinberg, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 101)
      - Military records, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 102)
      - Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 103)
      - Testimonies
        - Abstracts and indexes, 1950, 1953, undated (Box 8, Folder 104 - 105)
        - Cohn, Roy [examination of Crouch], undated (Box 8, Folder 106)
        - House Committee on Un-American Activities, 1949-1950 (Box 8, Folder 107)
        - Welch, Hoke [testimony about Crouch], 1953 (Box 8, Folder 108)
        - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 8, Folder 109)
      - Writings about Paul Crouch [by Harry Rand], 1953 (Box 8, Folder 110)
      - Writings by Paul Crouch, 1949-1955 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Cummings, William G.
      - Clippings, 1949, undated (Box 8, Folder 112)
      - Communist Party of the United States of America, 1945-1949 (Box 8, Folder 113)
      - Financial documents, 1946-1947 (Box 8, Folder 114)
      - Legal documents, statements, and testimonies, 1949-1954, undated (Box 8, Folder 115)
      - Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 116)
      - Miscellaneous, 1947-1952 (Box 8, Folder 117)
    - Cvetic, Matthew
      - Biographical information, 1939, 1950-1956, undated (Box 8, Folder 118 - 119)
      - Clippings, 1950-1962 (Box 8, Folder 120)
      - Correspondence [from Hyman Schlesinger to Frank Donner re: Cvetic], 1953-1955 (Box 8, Folder 121)
      - Kahn, Albert [statement re: Cvetic], undated (Box 9, Folder 122)
      - Notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 123)
      - Testimonies
        - Indexes, 1950-1956 (Box 9, Folder 124)
        - House Committee on Un-American Activities, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 125)
        - Miscellaneous, 1950, 1954, undated (Box 9, Folder 126 - 127)
      - Writings [includes "I Posed as a Communist for the FBI"], 1950 (Box 9, Folder 128)
    - Darcy, Sam, 1933-1949 (Box 9, Folder 129)
    - Davis, Charles, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 130)
    - Davis, David, undated (Box 9, Folder 131)
    - Demmerle, George
      - Biographical information, 1975, undated (Box 9, Folder 132)
      - Clippings [also includes information about Jane Alpert and Samuel Melville], 1970-1975 (Box 9, Folder 133)
      - FBI report, 1970, 1975, undated (Box 9, Folder 134 - 135)
      - Interviews, 1972, undated (Box 9, Folder 136)
      - Military record, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 137)
      - Police and criminal files, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 138)
      - Psychological file, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 139)
      - Testimony, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 140)
    - Desmond, Jeff [interviews and statements], 1970s (Box 10, Folder 141 - 142)
    - DiMaria, Samuel, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 143)
    - Diner, Sam, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 144)
    - Divale, William
      - Clippings, 1969, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 145)
      - Interviews, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 146 - 147)
      - Notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 148)
    - Dodd, Bella
      - Biographical information, 1940-1955 (Box 10, Folder 149)
      - Clippings, 1952-1956 (Box 10, Folder 150)
      - Testimony before the Subversive Activities Control Board, 1953 (Box 10, Folder 151)
    - Douglas, Boyd
      - Articles, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 152)
      - Clerks exhibit listing, undated (Box 10, Folder 153)
      - Court documents
        General note
        See: Series III. Subject Files, 1941-1992 Folder 180 - 193
        See: Series III. Subject Files, 1941-1992 Folder 194 - 215
      - Health records, 1964-1970 (Box 10, Folder 154)
      - Interview, undated (Box 10, Folder 155)
      - Notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 156 - 162)
      - Prison records, 1963-1970, undated (Box 11, Folder 163 - 167)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 11, Folder 168)
    - Dunham, Roger, 1954, undated (Box 11, Folder 169)